Rafael Sales

Brazil

rafaelcds@gmail.com | http://TheHeartBit.com | +55 85 8847 0206

SUMMARY

I'm a curious and challenge-driven Agile Software Engineer with 7 years of professional experience acting as Technical Lead, Mentor, and writing end-to-end Web Applications with Object Oriented code in Ruby on Rails, Java, JavaScript and Python. In the past 3 years I've been working remotely in Agile projects for US-based clients, spreading knowledge and onboarding newcomers.

I started writing my first lines of code when I was 12 years old and I've been doing it with more passion every new year, so I'm always reading and thinking about getting better at writing crafted and well-tested code for web applications, and also working hard to make these fulfill and benefit the properties of a real Distributed System.

A non-exhaustive list of my skill set: Object Oriented Design, Ruby on Rails 3 & 4, JavaScript, Java, Python, PostgreSQL, MySQL, NoSQL, REST/SOAP API design, TDD, Ruby and Java testing frameworks, Linux servers maintenance, Apache configuration, Clean Code, Code Review and Pair Programming.

Creator and writer of http://TheHeartBit.com
Personal GitHub: https://GitHub.com/RafaelSales
Creator and maintainer of projects at http://GitHub.com/HeartBits

Hobbies: Guitar player and love traveling - I live in Brazil and already visited US, UK and France.

EXPERIENCE

Stack Builders Inc., New York, US - Working remotely from Brazil Software Engineer

2013 - Present

Worked on several projects with teams varying from 3 to 15 developers.

At Stack Builders I had the pleasure to lead the development of multiple projects as well as craft code for applications with huge web traffic and amount of data.

Aside client projects, I also helped interviewing candidates (with live coding and technical review), brainstorming ideas for company-wide improvements, and also gave talk about technical subjects on internal R&D meetings.

Some of my responsibilities:

- Write crafted and automated-tested code in Ruby and JS, always with fine object oriented design
- Promote meetings and discussions to define important architectural changes, plan refactoring of legacy code and technical debts
- Attend estimation sessions, sprint planning, team retrospective and daily stand-ups
- Evaluate staging and production alerts through Airbrake, NewRelic and Nagios in order to prioritize the needed fixes
- Remote pair programming and onboard newcomers
- Maintain a number of unix-based servers on Rackspace and Amazon Web Services
- Maintain Ruby gems that are reused across applications
- · Coordinate deployments using Capistrano and CircleCI

- Have ideas and suggest stories to help client grow their business, improve application architecture and error handling
- Being skeptical in code reviews through GitHub and pairing in order to reduce chances of bugs and non-quality code to be merged
- · Identify rooms for improvement on the team to increase productivity and relationship with client

Techl Lead at NY Water Taxi

Renewed the NY Water Taxi website refactoring the backend and applying the look & feel designed by the client with responsive techniques and HTML5 features.

Mentored and coordinated the site development close to the client, reviewing code and pairing to help other developers be productive to meet client's deadline.

Consultant Developer and Tech Lead at Haystak Digital Marketing

Worked on two products of Haystak:

- SEO Platform: worked as technical lead on this application that monitors the performance of auto dealers in Google, Bing/Yahoo and Social Medias.
- Dynamic: worked as consultant and engineer on this application that generates ads dynamically in Google AdWords and BingAds.

Based in Ruby on Rails and Ember.js, both have interesting challenges such as keeping thousands of campaigns and keywords performance data up-to-date, display reports and graphs in a practical render time.

Besides working on regular stories, I was also responsible for scaling and making the platform stable, failproof and idempotent. Worked on multiple API integrations, such as BingAds, Google Analytics, Google AdWords, DoubleClick Bid Manager, AuthorityLabs, MOZ.com.

Tech Lead at Durst Organization

Developed a multi-tenant application, with CMS and pages export to PDF.

Mentored and coordinated the site development close to the client, reviewing code and pairing to help other developers be productive to meet client's deadline.

ThoughtWorks, Recife, Brazil Software Consultant

2012 - 2013

• OVE (Online Vehicle Exchange) is an online wholesale vehicle marketplace built with Ruby since Rails 1.

It's an agile distributed team where we practice lean, clean code, TDD, constant feedback and retrospectives. Here we are daily challenged to conciliate new features delivering, application improvements, killing technical debt and constant communication with the other offices involved. As the team is distributed, we have daily stand-ups and discussions with other devs, BAs and QAs through videoconference and stay highly available in Jabber, Skype and Google Hangout.

The application brings up a lot of challenges like maintaining and adding features to a huge codebase with automated tests while keeping it clear and clean, coordinating integration with various external systems, complex deploy, huge database, high website load, etc.

Some of the languages, frameworks, tools and techniques I've been working are: Ruby, JavaScript, Rails, Capistrano, Background Jobs, Resque, Redis, TDD, RSpec, REST, MySQL, GIT, Jenkins, Memcached, UNIX, Bash, Vim, pairing and Kanban.

As part of the onboarding process I had the opportunity to spend one month in US to meet the rest of the team, which is distributed across Chicago-IL, Atlanta-GA and Recife/Brazil. Working from home was sometimes necessary when I had to travel, which made acquire required skills and feel confortable to make this happen smoothly in a daily basis.

IVIA, Fortaleza, Brazil Senior Software Developer

2008 - 2012

 While working at IVIA I had the opportunity to acquire a wide knowledge of software development in general and be part of great teams that developed and delivered relevant projects for key local companies, like SEFAZ-CE, TRT-CE, Ministério da Cultura, Unimed Fortaleza, Camed, M. Dias Branco, TCE-Bahia and TCE-CE.

In addition to my role as a developer in the last year working at IVIA, I also practiced consulting skills with a couple clients, lead a team and coached junior developers.

The set of languages, frameworks and tools I worked with over the 4+ years at IVIA were: Java, JavaScript, Struts, JEE 5 and 6 (CDI, EJB, JPA2, JAX-WS, JAAS, JMS), JBoss AS 6 and 7, GlassFish 3, Hibernate, Spring (IoC, Security, DataSource and Transaction Management), PostgreSQL, Oracle, Aspect Oriented Programming, SOAP, JUnit, DBUnit, Selenium WebDriver, SVN and Eclipse IDE

Besides delivering software, I also gave training to co-workers at IVIA and BNB (Banco do Nordeste do Brasil) focused on Javascript, jQuery, AJAX and creating REST API with Python.

EDUCATION

Federal University of Ceará Bachelor

2008 - 2012

• I have a good academical background having done research around HPC (High Performance Computing) focused in Parallel Programming.